Hate crimes against religious minorities have become increasingly common in India.
Report after report have highlighted the rise of violent incidents against the
minorities in India. The recent data shows that among the minorities hate crimes
against Muslims have the largest volume with a 300% increase since right-wing
government came to power in the center in 2014. One of them is Jamiat Ulama-i-Hind
Hind, the oldest and largest socio-cultural organization of Indian
Muslims, which has been on the ground for long, combating hate crimes committed
against the country's religious minorities. And in this struggle, their
justice and empowerment initiative hopes to change the disturbing trends of the
increasing hate crimes against religious minorities. With the mission of
safeguarding their human rights and countering hate speech targeted against
them, JEM aims to ensure the implementation of equal rights, justice,
peace, religious tolerance and coexistence for all in the country. Their
objectives include developing a hate crime database, promoting the rule of
law and access to justice, upholding citizens security and human rights,
defending religious minorities and marginalized communities and promoting
peace-building and interfaith harmony. These objectives tie with our ultimate
goal of empowering the oppressed and wrongly persecuted and promoting a more
just and inclusive society in India. For all of this to come together, JEM has
four departments - Hate Crime Response Unit, Case Review Committee, Media Unit and
Legal Unit. And this is how our work channels through them. It begins with the
organization's reporting and ground networks when news about hate crimes is
first received. We believe in verifying cases ourselves rather than relying
solely on secondary sources. For this second step, local members of our Hate
Crime Response Unit are deployed on the ground to provide immediate aid and
collect testimonies from the victims. We also have our own website, a form to
report a hate crime and a helpline number. All the received and collected
information is then verified, analyzed and further listed under one of the seven
types of cases that we are equipped to handle, namely acts of hate, acts of
violence, attacks on religious places, police atrocities, discrimination,
exclusion and prejudice, state-sponsored discriminatory practices and media
manipulation and distortion of facts. At JEM, a specialized case review committee
carefully screens these cases to assess how to help with our limited resources.
And this is the final and most crucial part, intervention, which can fall into
either of the four umbrella categories - reporting, documentation, advocacy and
training and capacity building. With our diligent reporting, we bring forth policy
demands, appeal to figureheads and dignitaries by writing letters and grab
the media spotlight on these otherwise ignored issues. With facts out there, we
continue with meticulous documentation of each and every case. We maintain a hate
crime database, which documents alarming trends of hate crimes and
simultaneously aids in developing tailored solutions to combat these crimes.
In this regard, we also publish four quarterly reviews and an annual review every
year. All of this documentation offers evidence for our long-term strategy for
intervention, which is our advocacy for better legislation and policy making at
different levels. Some of our legally advocated interventions have had a
significant positive impact on the outcome of cases. At JEM, we also believe
in capacity-building and empowering people. For this, we aim to establish state,
city and town units in as many locations as possible. Well-versed in social
political dynamics, these units are trained to promptly identify and address
hate crimes and build trust and solidarity between different communities.
They play a critical role in countering hate crimes by providing local
presence, immediate assistance to victims and connecting them with legal and
victim assistance services. Through their tireless efforts, JEM works towards
empowering victims, promoting equality and fostering peace in India. Community
support is crucial in the endeavor to counter hate crimes and promote a more
inclusive society. Together, we can stand against discrimination and violence,
ensuring that every individual feels safe and protected, regardless of their
religious or social background. By supporting organizations like JEM and
actively participating in initiatives, promoting dialogue, understanding and
harmony, we can create a society where tolerance and acceptance prevail. Let us
join hands and become champions for justice, equality and peace, supporting
the good fight against hate.